<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <title>rebecca&#39;s blog</title>
  
  
  <link href="http://southjava.github.io/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  
  <link href="http://southjava.github.io/"/>
  <updated>2024-02-21T22:46:21.598Z</updated>
  <id>http://southjava.github.io/</id>
  
  <author>
    <name>rebecca</name>
    
  </author>
  
  <generator uri="https://hexo.io/">Hexo</generator>
  
  <entry>
    <title>classic cryptographic systems</title>
    <link href="http://southjava.github.io/2024/02/17/classic-cryptographic-systems/"/>
    <id>http://southjava.github.io/2024/02/17/classic-cryptographic-systems/</id>
    <published>2024-02-17T01:04:37.000Z</published>
    <updated>2024-02-21T22:46:21.598Z</updated>
    
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>This blog describes the principles of classic ciphers, perform cryptanalysis on classic ciphers, describe the principles of Steganography and the basic terminology of modern cryptosystems. Really a h-h-h-huge workload. Enjoy your crypto-journey. XD</p><span id="more"></span><!-- toc --><ul><li><a href="#basic-cryptanalysis">Basic Cryptanalysis</a></li><li><a href="#polyalphabetic-ciphers">Polyalphabetic ciphers.</a><ul><li><a href="#vigen%C3%A8re-cipher">Vigenère Cipher</a></li><li><a href="#vigenere-cipher-cryptanalysis">Vigenere Cipher: Cryptanalysis</a><ul><li><a href="#kasisky-test">Kasisky test</a></li><li><a href="#index-of-coincidence">Index of coincidence</a></li></ul></li><li><a href="#rotor-cipher-machines">Rotor cipher machines</a></li><li><a href="#rail-fence-cipher">Rail Fence cipher</a></li><li><a href="#columnar-transposition-cipher">Columnar Transposition Cipher</a></li></ul></li></ul><!-- tocstop --><blockquote><p>“<em>most systems diffuse the key into the data. DES does this and the DES  cracks rely on this to break into the code.</em>“</p></blockquote><p><strong>The best way to transmit secure data safely is to: Compress the data, encrypt and add error detection &amp; recovery.</strong></p><h1><span id="basic-cryptanalysis">Basic Cryptanalysis</span></h1><p>Cryptanalysis usually involves a variety of techniques.</p><blockquote><ol><li>For example, <strong>frequency</strong> analysis* can indicate possible letters, but this can be enhanced by cribs. In English, the letter ‘E’ is the most frequently used letter, followed by ‘T’, ‘A’, ‘O’, ‘I’, and so on. By analyzing the frequency of letters in the ciphertext, a cryptanalyst can make educated guesses about the possible plaintext characters.</li><li>A “<strong>crib</strong>” is a known sequence of letters or words – e.g. in English the letter u almost always follows q.</li><li>We can also make guesses about common words based on the context of letters.</li></ol><ul><li>Unfortunately a strength of a short message is its difficulty of applying frequency analysis, Moreover, cipher makers usually employ some additional tricks on the text for example: break up the text into words that do not match the original word lengths – or even a stream of characters.</li></ul></blockquote><ol><li><p><strong>The vowels A E I O are normally high frequency, U is moderate and Y is low frequency.</strong></p><p><em>Try to analyze a cipher in terms of vowels and consonants alone before committing values to letters.</em></p></li><li><p><strong>Letters contacting low frequency letters are usually vowels.</strong></p></li><li><p><strong>Letters showing a wide variety of contact are usually vowels.</strong></p></li><li><p><strong>In repeated digrams (pairs of letters), one letter is usually a vowel.</strong></p></li><li><p><strong>In reversed digrams - e.g. VX, XV, one letter is normally a vowel.</strong></p></li><li><p><strong>Doubled consonants are usually bordered by vowels and vice versa.</strong></p></li><li><p><strong>It is unusual to find more than five consonants in a row.</strong></p></li><li><p><strong>Vowels do not often contact one another.</strong></p></li></ol><h1><span id="polyalphabetic-ciphers">Polyalphabetic ciphers.</span></h1><blockquote><p> System: Alternate between the cipher alphabets C1 and C2</p></blockquote><h2><span id="vigenère-cipher">Vigenère Cipher</span></h2><p>The idea is to have 26 cipher alphabets all shifted by a different amount from the plaintext alphabet, this is managed using a Vigenère square:</p><blockquote><ol><li><p>Consider the set of all 26 Caesar ciphers: { C<sub>a</sub>, C<sub>b</sub>, … , C<sub>z</sub>}</p></li><li><p>Choose a Key: e.g. <em>Rebecca</em></p></li><li><p>Encrypt the plaintext letter by letter using C<sub>r</sub>,</p><p>C<sub>e</sub>,C<sub>b</sub>,C<sub>e</sub>,C<sub>c</sub>,C<sub>c</sub>,C<sub>a</sub> in turn.</p></li><li><p>Repeat from start after the last C<sub>a</sub></p></li><li><p>Decryption simply works in reverse.</p></li></ol></blockquote><h2><span id="vigenere-cipher-cryptanalysis">Vigenere Cipher: Cryptanalysis</span></h2><p><strong>Basic approach</strong></p><blockquote><ol><li>Find the length of the key.</li><li>Divide the message into that many simple substitution encryptions.</li><li>Use frequency analysis to solve the resulting simple substitutions.</li></ol></blockquote><p>But how to find the key?</p><blockquote><ol><li>Kasisky test</li><li>Index of coincidence (Friedman)</li></ol></blockquote><h3><span id="kasisky-test">Kasisky test</span></h3><blockquote><p><strong>Concept</strong>: plaintext words separated by multiples of the key length are encoded in the same way.</p></blockquote><blockquote><p><em><strong>It is worth noting if the distance between the repeated pattern is not a multiple of the key, this test will reveal nothing.</strong></em></p></blockquote><p><strong>Algorithm</strong></p><ol><li>Search for pairs of identical segments of length at least 3</li><li>Record distances between the two segments: ∆1, ∆2, … .</li><li>The key length (m) should divide the gcd( ∆1, ∆2, …). (the greatest common divisor)</li></ol><p><strong>Limitations</strong></p><blockquote><ul><li><strong>Coincidences:</strong> Random coincidences in the ciphertext can lead to incorrect identification of the key length if not enough repeated sequences are analyzed.</li><li><strong>Short Keys and Texts:</strong> The Kasiski Test is less effective for very short keys or texts, where repeated sequences are less likely to occur.</li><li><strong>Manual Analysis:</strong> Before the advent of computers, the Kasiski Test required tedious manual work, but now software can automate much of the process.</li></ul></blockquote><h3><span id="index-of-coincidence">Index of coincidence</span></h3><p><strong>IC is defined</strong> to be the probability that two randomly selected letters from a text will be identical.</p><p>The formula for the index of coincidence for any text is:<br>$$<br>IC &#x3D; \frac{\sum_{i&#x3D;A}^{Z} f_i(f_i - 1)}{N(N-1)}<br>$$</p><blockquote><p><em>N</em> is the total number of letters in the text.</p><p><em>f</em><sub><em>i</em></sub>  is the frequency of letter <em>i</em> in the text. (i.e the number of occurrences ) </p></blockquote><p>If a ciphertext is a mono-alphabetic substitution then it will have similar frequencies (albeit not the same letters) as the standard alphabet.</p><p>There is a measure called the ‘Index of Coincidence’ which can be calculated to see whether our cryptogram frequencies are similar to normal English.</p><blockquote><p>Normal written English has an IC of around 0.066. Entirely random text has an IC near 1&#x2F;26 &#x3D; 0.038.</p></blockquote><p>IC is unique for each language, for an English text, IC is around 0.065.</p><p> You can use this metric to find the key length of a Vigenerecipher, as follows:</p><blockquote><p>Assume you have a textY&#x3D;y1y2y3..yn.</p><ol><li>Make a guess of the key length (e.g. m)</li><li>Arrange the text into a matrix of m rows</li><li>Calculate IC for rach row(Y<sub>1</sub>-Y<sub>m</sub>)</li><li>If the width of the matrix is a multiple of the actual key length than:</li></ol></blockquote><p>$$<br>IC(Yi) \approx 0.065 \mid \forall 1\le i \le m<br>$$</p><blockquote><ol start="5"><li>Repeat the process again until you find the correct key</li></ol></blockquote><h2><span id="rotor-cipher-machines">Rotor cipher machines</span></h2><blockquote><p>Rotor cipher machines are fascinating devices used for encrypting and decrypting secret messages. They played a crucial role in military and diplomatic communications, especially during the early to mid-20th century. The most famous example of such a machine is the Enigma machine, used by Nazi Germany during World War II.</p></blockquote><p>It was based on rotors whose movement produced ever-changing alphabetic substitutions.</p><p>More abstractly: the number of ways of choosing m pairs out of n objects is:</p><p><img src="/../img/classic-cryptographic-systems/image-20240221140534711.png" alt="image-20240221140534711"></p><h2><span id="rail-fence-cipher">Rail Fence cipher</span></h2><p>Encryption : The Letters of the message are written diagonally over a number of  rows (rails) then read off cipher row by row.</p><p>The key for the rail fence cipher is just the number of rails.</p><p><img src="/../img/classic-cryptographic-systems/rail.png" alt="rail"></p><h2><span id="columnar-transposition-cipher">Columnar Transposition Cipher</span></h2><p>Encryption: the message is written out in rows of a fixed length and then  read out again column by column. Both the width of the rows and the permutation of the columns are usually defined by a keyword.</p>]]></content>
    
    
    <summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;This blog describes the principles of classic ciphers, perform cryptanalysis on classic ciphers, describe the principles of Steganography and the basic terminology of modern cryptosystems. Really a h-h-h-huge workload. Enjoy your crypto-journey. XD&lt;/p&gt;</summary>
    
    
    
    <category term="cryptography" scheme="http://southjava.github.io/categories/cryptography/"/>
    
    
    <category term="classic cryptographic systems" scheme="http://southjava.github.io/tags/classic-cryptographic-systems/"/>
    
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>crypt-introduction</title>
    <link href="http://southjava.github.io/2024/02/17/crypt-introduction/"/>
    <id>http://southjava.github.io/2024/02/17/crypt-introduction/</id>
    <published>2024-02-17T00:07:06.000Z</published>
    <updated>2024-02-17T01:52:05.934Z</updated>
    
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>This blog introduces the basic concepts and history of cryptography. :)</p><span id="more"></span><!-- toc --><ul><li><a href="#what-is-cryptography">what is cryptography</a></li><li><a href="#a-brief-history">A brief history</a><ul><li><a href="#ancient-cryptography">Ancient Cryptography</a></li><li><a href="#the-middle-ages">The Middle Ages</a></li><li><a href="#the-renaissance">The Renaissance</a></li><li><a href="#the-20th-century">The 20th Century</a></li><li><a href="#modern-cryptography">Modern Cryptography</a></li></ul></li></ul><!-- tocstop --><h1><span id="what-is-cryptography">what is cryptography</span></h1><p>cryptography is the science of writing with goal of hiding the meaning of the message.</p><blockquote><p>provides the basic building blocks to construct secure systems. <strong>However</strong>, it doesn’t provide solutions to all security problems. It is only reliable if implemented properly.</p></blockquote><p><strong>Cryptanalysis</strong> - analyzing (breaking)  secrets.</p><blockquote><p><em>Cryptanalysis is what attacker does. Decipher or decryption is what legitimate receiver does.</em></p></blockquote><h1><span id="a-brief-history">A brief history</span></h1><p>The history of cryptography is fascinating, encompassing ancient techniques developed for secure communication, evolving through the ages to the sophisticated digital encryption methods we use today. </p><h2><span id="ancient-cryptography">Ancient Cryptography</span></h2><blockquote><p>The earliest forms of cryptography were simple and manual. One of the oldest known methods is the Caesar cipher, attributed to Julius Caesar, who used it to communicate with his generals. This method involved shifting the letters of the alphabet by a set number to encode messages.</p></blockquote><h2><span id="the-middle-ages">The Middle Ages</span></h2><blockquote><p>During the Middle Ages, cryptography became more sophisticated. The scytale, an encryption device used by the Spartans, consisted of a cylinder around which a strip of parchment was wound. The message could only be read when wrapped around a cylinder of the same diameter.</p></blockquote><h2><span id="the-renaissance">The Renaissance</span></h2><blockquote><p>The Renaissance saw significant advancements in cryptography. Leon Battista Alberti is credited with inventing the polyalphabetic cipher, a more complex system that used multiple alphabets to encrypt a message. This method significantly increased the difficulty of decryption without the key.</p></blockquote><h2><span id="the-20th-century">The 20th Century</span></h2><blockquote><p>The 20th century witnessed the rise of mechanical and then electronic cryptographic devices. The most famous among these was the Enigma machine, used by Germany during World War II. It was a sophisticated piece of machinery that provided a high level of security, which was eventually broken by Allied cryptanalysts, including Alan Turing.</p></blockquote><h2><span id="modern-cryptography">Modern Cryptography</span></h2><blockquote><p>Today, cryptography is largely computer-based, with complex algorithms ensuring the security of digital communications. The invention of public-key cryptography in the 1970s by Whitfield Diffie and Martin Hellman marked a revolutionary shift, enabling secure communication between parties without sharing a secret key.</p></blockquote><p><img src="/../img/crypt-introduction/cryptography_history-1708130357907-1.png" alt="cryptography_history"></p><figure class="highlight cmd"><table><tr><td class="gutter"><pre><span class="line">1</span><br></pre></td><td class="code"><pre><span class="line">a timeline that illustrates the history of cryptography, from its ancient beginnings with the Caesar cipher, through significant developments like the scytale, the Alberti cipher disk, and the Enigma machine, up to modern public-key cryptography.</span><br></pre></td></tr></table></figure>]]></content>
    
    
    <summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;This blog introduces the basic concepts and history of cryptography. :)&lt;/p&gt;</summary>
    
    
    
    <category term="cryptography" scheme="http://southjava.github.io/categories/cryptography/"/>
    
    
    <category term="cryptography-history" scheme="http://southjava.github.io/tags/cryptography-history/"/>
    
  </entry>
  
</feed>
